Guide to the Madeleine Alcover Cyrano research materials and Academic papers, 1957-2014 MS 631
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Madeleine Alcover Cyrano research materials and Academic papers
1957-2014
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Alcover, Madeleine
MS 631
9 Linear Feet (9 boxes + 1 oversize folder)
This collection contains typescripts, proofs, correspondence, microfilm, and notecards of Madeleine Alcover for her critical editions and studies on Cyrano de Bergerac; Cyrano's family, as well as his writer-friends Charles d'Assoucy, Le Royer de Prades, Henry Le Bret, and others. The collection also contains documents and correspondence related to Alcover's academic career.
Biographical Note
Dr. Madeleine Alcover was born in Casablanca, Morocco on October 27, 1938. She received a Diplôme d'études supérieures de lettres modernes (magna cum laude) and a Doctorate in French Literature (summa cum laude) from the University of Bordeaux. She began her teaching career at Indiana University from 1967-1975 before coming to Rice University in 1971. Specializing in 17th and 18th century French literature, she contributed to the current understanding of the life, times, and works of Cyrano de Bergerac, a subject she would continue to pursue in Paris archives even in the years after her retirement in 2004.
Dr. Alcover garnered international recognition for the five books she published over the course of her career, and of articles on Bayle, Corneille, Fénelon, Furetière, Guilleragues, Madeleine de Scudéry, and Voltaire. Her published books are: Cyrano de Bergerac (1968); La Pensée philosophique et scientifique de Cyrano de Bergerac (1971); L'Autre Monde ou Les Estats et Empires de la Lune (1977); Poullain de la Barre, une aventure philosophique (1981); and Cyrano relu et corrigé (1990). Dr. Alcover passed away on August 27, 2014.
Savinien Cyrano de Bergerac, (born March 6, 1619, Paris—died July 28, 1655, Paris), was a French satirist and dramatist whose works combining political satire and science-fantasy inspired a number of later writers. He has been the basis of many romantic but unhistorical legends, of which the best known is Edmond Rostand's play Cyrano de Bergerac (1897), in which he is portrayed as a gallant and brilliant but shy and ugly lover, possessed (as in fact he was) of a remarkably large nose.
As a young man, Cyrano joined the company of guards and was wounded at the Siege of Arras in 1640. But he gave up his military career in the following year to study under the philosopher and mathematician Pierre Gassendi. Under the influence of Gassendi's scientific theories and libertine philosophy, Cyrano wrote his two best known works, Histoire comique des états et empires de la lune and Histoire comique des états et empires du soleil (Eng. trans. A Voyage to the moon: with some account of the Solar World, 1754). These stories of imaginary journeys to the Moon and Sun, published posthumously in 1656 and 1662, satirize 17th-century religious and astronomical beliefs, which saw man and the world as the center of creation.
Savinien Cyrano de Bergerac. (2015). In Encyclopædia Britannica. Retrieved from http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/148648/Savinien-Cyrano-de-Bergerac" show="new" title="http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/148648/Savinien-Cyrano-de-Bergerac">http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/148648/Savinien-Cyrano-de-Bergerac
Scope and Contents
This collection contains typescripts, proofs, correspondence, microfilm, and notecards of Madeleine Alcover for her critical editions and studies on Cyrano de Bergerac; Cyrano's family, as well as his writer-friends Charles d'Assoucy, Le Royer de Prades, Henry Le Bret, and others. The collection also contains documents and correspondence related to Alcover's academic career.
Access restrictions
This material is open for research except for one folder which is marked as restricted.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated by the estate of Madeleine Alcover in 2014.
Index Terms
Subjects
Authors; Research; French literature; Literature
Document Types
manuscripts (document genre); typescripts
Places
France
Subjects (Persons)
Cyrano de Bergerac
- Series I. Works and research materials, 1960-2004, undated; 261456
  - Sub-Series I. Cyrano de Bergerac research materials, 260126
    - Articles, 260128 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Articles: Jordan's edition of L'autre Monde ou les Etats et Empires de la Lune, translated, 1970; 260131 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Articles: Histoire Comique, 260132 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - Notes on Cyrano, 260133 (Box 1, Folder 6-10)
    - Notes on Cyrano attribution and datation, 260134 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
    - Articles: Cyrano family, 260135 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Notes on Cyrano family, 260136 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Cyrano: Sens, 260874 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Cyrano correspondence, 1978-1990; 260137 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Cyrano correspondence, 1995-1996; 260138 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Cyrano correspondence, 1997; 260139 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Cyrano correspondence, 1998; 260141 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Cyrano correspondence, 1999; 260142 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Cyrano correspondence, 2000-2003; 260143 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Cyrano correspondence, 2004; 260145 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Cyrano correspondence: author royalties from Honore-Champion edition, 2001-2014; 260147 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Cyrano correspondence, 260149 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Corrections and notes on drafts, 260151 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Typescripts: Draft of Cyrano relu et corrigé, 1988; 260153 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Typescripts: Draft of Slatkine edition of L'Autre Monde ou les etats et empires de la Lune, October 1999; 260154 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
    - First proof of Slatkine Edition, 260155 (Box 2, Folder 14-17)
    - First proof of novels, Slatkine edition, December 5, 1997; 260156 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Second proof of novels, Slatkine edition, 260157 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Draft of Slatkine edition, 260158 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Draft of glossary, 260159 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Final proof of Slatkine edition, 260161 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
    - Proof of Slatkine edition, 2004; 260163 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Drafts 2 and 3, L'autre Monde et le Libestinage Erudit, 260165 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - First draft Slatkine edition, Lune and Soleil, 260168 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Fragment de Physique, variations, biographical elements, 260173 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Oeuvres Completes, 260175 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Lune and Soleil with notes, 260177 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - First version Lune and Soleil, 260179 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Second version, Lune and Soleil, May 1997; 260171 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Lune and Soleil, 260181 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Cyrano et la posture philosophique, 260183 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Unknown edition, 260164 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Typescripts [Alcover?], 260185 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Lectures de Cyrano de Bergerac: Les États et Empires de la Lune et du Soleil, 2004; 260873 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Published Works, 260189
      - Cyrano de Bergerac: L'autre Monde ou les états et empires de la lune (pre-printing copy), 1977; 260191 (Box 4)
      - Cyrano de Bergerac: L'autre Monde ou les états et empires de la lune with handwritten annotations, 1977; 260193 (Box 4)
      - Cyrano relu et corrigé with annotations, 1990; 260195 (Box 4)
      - Cyrano de Bergerac: les États et empires de la lune et du soleil (avec le Fragment de Physique); Champion Classiques edition, 2004; 260198 (Box 4)
  - Sub-Series II. D'Assoucy, de Prades, Le Bret research materials, 260200
    - D'Assoucy notes, 260201 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - D'Assoucy typescripts, 260204 (Box 4, Folder 2-4)
    - Jean Royer de Prades Articles, 260206 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - de Prades Notes, 260207 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
    - de Prades: Marie de la Tour articles, 260208 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - de Prades: Marie de la Tour notes, 260209 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - de Prades: Epernon notes, 260210 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - de Prades typescripts and drafts [Alcover?], 260211 (Box 4, Folder 11-12)
    - Le Bret articles, 260212 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Le Bret notes, 260214 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Le Bret: Montauban notes, 260216 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Le Bret typescripts, 260218 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Le Bret typescripts [Alcover?], 260219 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sub-Series III. Other research materials, 260221
    - Alchemy articles, 260222 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Alchemy notes, 260223 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Arpajon notes, 260225 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Beaumarchais notes, 260226 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Bellanger notes, 260227 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Berthier notes, 260228 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Bosse: Oeuvres Graves-femmes, culture, 260235 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Bourdelet notes, 260237 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Burlesque Notes, 260243 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Canada notes, 260244 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Caran notes, 260245 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Casteljaloux notes, 260246 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Company St. Sacrement notes, 260247 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Cuigny notes, 260248 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Daillon de Lude notes, 260249 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Davisson notes, 260250 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Davity notes, 260251 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Derrida notes, 260252 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Descartes articles, 260253 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Descartes notes, 260254 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Gassendi notes, 260255 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Heraldry and Coats of Arms notes, 260256 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Libraries - bibliographies, materials, 260257 (Box 5, Folder 27-28)
    - Le Livre Abominable notes, 260258 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Maupeon notes, 260263 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Mauroy notes, 260259 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Millet notes, 260261 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Mothe le Voyer notes, 260265 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Notaires/ Minutiers notes, 260266 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Pascal notes, 260267 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Phonetics notes, 260268 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Polyeucte articles, 260269 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Polyeucte notes, 260270 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Poullain article: De l'Egalite des deux sexes, Discours Physique and moral, 260271 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - Poullain La Barre notes, 260272 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - Prevot notes, 260273 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Prisons, hospitals, and police notes, 260274 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - Reception of works notes, 260313 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Regnault notes, 260314 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Religion notes, 260315 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Robineau notes, 260316 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Royalty/Bourbon Family articles, 260328 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Royalty notes, 260329 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Scarron notes, 260385 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Somaiville Affair notes, 260386 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - St. Marthe Family notes, 260389 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Swift and Moliere notes, 260390 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Transcriptions, 260391 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Utopia notes, 260392 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Writing, Attribution, Literary techniques articles, 260393 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Writing, Literature, and Criticism notes, 260394 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Miscellaneous articles, 260403 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Miscellaneous notes, 260406 (Box 6, Folder 16-18)
    - Typescripts: Index des Noms et des Ouvrages Anonymes, 260407 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Typescripts: L'indecence de Savoir, 260408 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Unidentified typescripts and drafts [Alcover?], 260409 (Box 6, Folder 21-22)
  - Sub-Series IV. Correspondence, 260429
    - 1960-69, 260584 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - 1970-79, 260586 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - 1980-89, 260587 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - 1990-94, 260589 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - 1995-99, 260591 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 2000-04, 260592 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 2005-09, 260594 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - 2010-14, 260596 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - No date, 260598 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Sub-Series V. Note Cards, 260431
    - Cyrano, 260611 (Box 7)
    - Descartes, 260612 (Box 7)
    - Gassendi, 260613 (Box 7)
    - Others, 260614 (Box 7)
  - Sub-Series VI. Microfilm, Microfiche, digital formats, 260619
    - Cyrano: Microfilm, microfiche, CDs, Floppy disks (2 boxes), 260621 (Box 8)
    - Le Bret, D'Assoucy, Royer de Prades: Microfilm, CDs (1 box), 260625 (Box 8)
    - Other Research: Microfilm, Microfiche, CDs (2 boxes), 260631 (Box 8-9)
- Series II. Career & Personal, 1957-2014, undated; 260425
  - Curriculum Vitae, [1988], 1999, 2004, n.d.; 260757 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Attestation of Education, 1957-1967; 260672 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Indiana University: Tenure, Evaluations, Voltaire book, 1967-1975; 260673 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Rice University, 1977-2004; 260674 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Rice Salary information, 1976-2003; 260758 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Rice: Class materials, 1975-2002; 260759 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Rice: FREN 407: French History through film (Restricted), Spring 2004; 260760 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Rice Graduate French Program, 261376 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Rice: newsclippings, 1982-1991; 260761 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Rice: Theatre productions, 1991; 260762 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: other universities, 1968-1991; 260763 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: recommendations, 1969-2006; 260764 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: recommendations, 260765 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Research: money and leave, 1970-1997; 260766 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - University of Cape Town (teaching), 1994; 260767 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Camargo Foundation Residential Grant, 1996; 260768 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Societe des Gens de Lettres de France, 1996; 260769 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - D'Assoucy Colloquium, 2004; 260770 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - Critical reception of Alcover works, 1970-2003; 260771 (Box 9, Folder 19)
  - Critical reception of Alcover works, n.d.; 260772 (Box 9, Folder 20)
  - Critical reviews by Alcover, 1984-1994; 260773 (Box 9, Folder 21)
  - Articles published by Alcover, 1971-1987; 260774 (Box 9, Folder 22)
  - Articles published by Alcover, 1990-1999; 260775 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Articles published by Alcover, 2000-2006; 260776 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - Published works: Poulain de la Barre: Une Aventure Philosophique, 1981; 260778 (Box 9, Folder 25)
  - Personal, 1995-2006, n.d.; 260777 (Box 9, Folder 26)
  - Oversize folder, 260837 (Box 9)
    General
    Diplôme de docteur, 1967 Le Theatre, Cyrano, n.d.